Now you remember but how many class we have
for branded algorithms 4 you will try okay
fine because the rate at which I am going
I will probably need one more class just to
finish the two proofs I wanted to do today
so which should mean I would need one more
extra class for finishing all of brand is
did we do 4 class last year 6 yeah I think
I we did we had visiting faculty you were
talk okay. We have oh good fine then I am
not too bad of okay.
.
Okay since of writing the compression 2ln
n/s all over right so I am defining that as
Cns okay then if I write Cn-1s it is ln of
n-1/s and then I can do Cn, s + n so on forth
right I can just like a function just substitute
that make my life little easier right so the
goal now as I mentioned earlier is to upper
bound this expectation right so I will never
play a suboptimal on more than this many times
okay that is necessarily what we are try to
show okay so one other notation I will just
adopt the notation used in the proof here
even though we introduced a different notation
in the previous class where the same thing
get makes it little easier for me.
This notation indicates a I mean it denotes
a random variable corresponding to that indicator
right so this is a random variable whose value
1 if IT = I whose value sis 0 if IT = not
equal to I okay so whatever is this I will
put in some kind of events of here later right
so if IT = I then what does it mean it means
that okay fine I apologies for the confusion
this yeah so when I say In = I okay it means
that at time n I played MI right so if this
the hole expression within curly braces will
be one if at time at n I played MI it will
be 0 if at time n I played arm not I okay
so there are couple of things which we can
observe about this so at any instant I In
= I will be 1 for some I for everything it
will be .
Right because at very time instant I can play
only arm and at every time instance In I will
play at least 1 arm so it will be 1 for 1
of the arms so everything it will be 0 okay
this yeah the paper is not really the most
accessible of papers out there right so if
you are going to read it on your own you will
have to do some work okay so these are not
I mean they just assume that to your are all
really smart people reading the paper so since
some of the gabs that you will have to fill
in yourself right I am just doing one of the
proofs in the papers so if you want to read
the rest of the paper and understand all the
theorems and all the algorithms that they
describe in the paper.
So you will need to some additional work okay
so L is some arbiter positive integer so I
start by saying this t as a running variable
okay so the number of times I played arm I
up till the nth instant will be one which
I get from the initialization + k+1 obviously
I could have played that ram again in the
first K times right in the first k times I
will play each arm only once right so am I
also I would have also played once so in the
first skate trails the S will be just 1 so
I just have that 1 there and from the k +
trail till the nth trail I add the number
of times this variable is 1 what does it mean
number of times I have taken arm I rights
so I M – I will be 1 when ever take arm
I so I just sum this up so that so that the
number of times I played arm I is what I get
right.
Is it fine this expression is fine okay this
is the only directly inductive path that we
have here soon after this whatever you do
or these are standard tricks that people play
to bound random variables okay so to actually
tell you about the general techniques all
of this I recommend you take the ATTCO course
because about third of the course is all about
how to do proofs like this right how many
of you have ATTCO already advanced techniques
in theoretical computer science theory of
computation.
Okay that is a course that Jayala Srama teaches
in the CS department so it is very relevant
to lot of ml reaches because more lot, machine
learning has become like randomized algorithms
right so if people teach you how to analysis
randomize algorithms you can take the same
ideas and you algorithms machine learning
algorithm as well so lot of the tools that
are developed there are useful here and many
of the things that we do here right essentially
have their roots in the kind of analysis that
people do for randomized algorithms okay.
Any way we so we will start by doing that
so I have an orbiter number l okay I say that
okay fine let us assume that I played that
arm L time okay then let us start counting
right so assuming that up till the M- 1 step
okay I have L or greater than L right only
then I will count this sample so at some point
I have discovered the I have pulled arm I
okay should I add it to my count or not what
I do I go head and look at the cumulative
count so far if the cumulative count is L
or higher I Add it to my count if it is below
L I do not add it to my count because I am
any way starting count from L okay.
So this is slightly different way of doing
that this I will star the count from some
arbitrary number give that I have taken that
arbitrary number already right so later on
we will since now are going to bound this
expression assuming that at least L time I
have taken the arm right and then we will
drive a bound for L so that we get whatever
probability we want okay so that is idea behind
doing this so this I can now derive a bound
for this assuming I have done at least L time
right then I will go back and find what is
that value of L so that I get whatever probabilities
I want right whatever grantees I want I will
go and find that L okay that essentially we
are going to do here.
Okay I just need more notation here write
this let me try this any way so when am I
going to take arm I right when will I take
arm I when arm I has the highest right arm
I has the highest value for this quantity
right when will I take arm I when in that
as the highest value.
.
For this quantity among all the arms specifically
I will take arm I only when Q+ C so that root
term is now C right that root there is what
I have written as C so I will take arm I only
when Q+ that C term is greater than Q ( A*
+ the C term corresponding to S term.
.
Yes that is why I have lesser than or equal
to here see at especially this should be 2
right in fact it as larger than everything
else but at least it has to be larger than
S * right so it has been every other action
but like he lightly pointed outer so this
is the larger set there when I will actually
be taking action but that is okay because
I am trying to upper bound it right I am trying
to give an exact number because trying to
give exact number make it two involve right
I am just trying to give an upper bound so
I'm saying very specifically I am looking
at the best arm I am saying that this should
be better than the best arm.
At least right so anything else we need have
will still have this right that condition
is also there so will but that conation back
in and what does this curly bracket mean it
is the curly bracket is a random variable
that indicates the value of 1 and the expression
within the curly bracket is true it will have
value of 0 and expression with the curly bracket
is falls so essentially this summation counts
how may time this in equality become true
after I as been taken L times nice so that
I what we did here right so this counting
is whatever we are doing here is after L times
I has been taken because L I have added here
as a count so like vise I am counting the
number of times is in equality becomes true
after I has been taken L times.
So this is essentially what I have so far
right. Back here this entire thing take another
seat vacant here if you want to move as well
you can see everything you guys are fine right
no not to complain because I will tell you
there is row vacant here no cannot you see
what I have warren or do not understand what
I have written well sun scripts become small
right so right then large then it becomes
confusing so that is Cm- 1 for people who
cannot read it I am reading it that Cm -1
, T A*M-1.
That is basically the number of times I have
played A * until the M-1 nth point right note
that I do not have to know this because I
do not know what is A* right this is just
the there but you know the there exists A
* right and I know that my I as to have better
whatever into that quantity then A* let so
it is just that right I do not know I do not
need to know which is A* okay just do not
get confused by the fact that I'm using A*
in the proof right did you get that CM-1 , TA*M-1
and this CM-1 , TI (m-1) no A* is a true.
Bets action which you do not know anything
about right for reader we have to compare
again so true best action right so we are
comparing against the true best action right
okay so far so good people can who could not
see heared me right and people understand
what is going on right so now we will I'm
shifting over here.
.
Writing one line I am talking for 10 minutes
man really we too have an additional index
for the Q-function for us to say this things,
right. What I write there is M-1 so the Q-function
at step M-1 okay I really need that additional
thing because Q keeps changing over time right
so I need to know at what stage I am talking
about the Q-function, so at that point I am
talking about the Q-function at the M-1 stage,
right. Remember that the Q-function at the
M-1 stage can be the same as the Q-function
at the M stage if I had not taken the action
previous.
At the M-1 stage if I am not taking action
A for action I then at the M stage also the
Q-function of action A will be the same it
will interchange, right just you have to be
careful about how you interpret the index
and I hope I also do not mess it up when I
do this lecture. No so we do read the different
interpretation for and I do need an additional
notation I follow this for that
because we need to what we need to insert
into this bound here.
Is the number of time I have taken A* so far,
right what I need to insert into this one,
is the number of times I have taken A* so
far which is TA* M-1 right and so it become
a little combustion now this can be is this
will be TA* or X okay fine we can get away
with that. If it is a little weird expression
so what I am saying here is okay take the
minimum of this expression okay overall time
instant 0 to end.
Take the maximum of this expression right
for all time instant L to M okay and look
at the number of times one will be had on
the other, right. This will be on over count
of that event this is clear right but here
I am talking about this quantity being higher
than this quantity at that particular instant
right I am talking about some time M-1 where
the quantity for A* was lesser than the quantity
for write.
Talking about sometime instant M-1 at which
this happened here what I am talking about,
okay at a time M-1 right I look at all the
A* values I have had in the previous time
step okay, I will take the least of that,
right and I will take all the I values Qi
values I have added in the previous time step
I will take the maths of that okay.
If the maths of this is greater than the min
of that then I will count that has 1 right
so can you convince yourself that, that event
will certainly be counted right because at
that instant the values already greater so
obviously the maths will be greater than the
min so if this is not the Min right the Min
should be lesser than this and if this is
not the maths then the maths should be greater
than this.
So if this value is greater than this value
then the some quantity greater than this value
will certainly be greater than some quantity
lesser than this value right you can see t
that right, so this is just the over count
of that event, right why am I writing this
over count? Because it makes it easier for
me to sorry now that is the event right the
curly brackets makes it easier for me to write
a expression.
Yeah what is it, one second I will come let
me finish yeah 0 <S<M L<= S less than because
L because I am I have that condition there
right I have to I have to take this atleast
L times, so the first L time what happens
I do not worry so I will remove that right
so only after that I am worried about, but
this will be an over count okay this will
be an over count of that. So little tricky
here so know the proof actually assumes that
at this point, okay.
I have taken this at least S times not TES
or S times okay the it is mainly because this
is the notation translation problem but we
will see we work with this and then I will
probably adjust the results later, right.
But we are reading the proof I am just telling
you there is a mismatch in the notation that
we have used so far, okay. But this is the
neat trick that we have noted, right. We have
taken rid of all the Min Max and everything,
right,
So what are we doing here so assume that the
Min occurs at some index right let us call
that index I do not p1 let we assume that
the Max occurs at some index say P2 right,
so now what I am doing here is I am summing
over all possible indices for A when I am
summing over all possible indices for I, correct.
So the combination P1, P2 will occur somewhere
because I am summing over all possible indices,
right.
At some point I would have use P1 for S and
P2 for SA, correct because I am summing over
all possible indices right so what was P1,
P1 was the one for which this minimum was
achieved P2 was the one for which this maximum
was achieved, so when I am summing over S
at some point S will have P1 at some point
Si will have P2 right, at that point this
expression will surely be true because I know
from the Min and Max argument that we have
earlier that will be true.
So I will certainly be counting this right
I will be over counting I will be counting
other things also but I will certainly be
counting this, so essentially so far we have
not lost anything we are essentially still
be maintaining at as Upper bond okay, so we
started of with this event right now we have
done a lot of simplifications and kept loosening
the bound to this was a strict equality and
there was nothing here, right.
This was strict equality no approximation
here, so from there at every step I am essentially
counting a larger and larger event, now the
thing is I have come to a point where I have
a simple enough expression right that I can
try to bound directly now, okay. So you can
start thinking know this kind of should lead
you to the shun of opting bond I can use the
bound shun of opting bound to try and bound
this expression.
This is simple enough expression, okay. So
this is true okay this is true when can this
happen? So my claim is this can be true if
one of several conditions hold right, so this
can be true if, okay this can be true if I
am either I am grossly under estimating my
optimal actions value, right. So this is my
optimal actions estimate now this is the true
value right so the true value minus the confidence
bound.
Are other way around think about it, right.
This Qs(A*) plus the confidence bound is less
than the true value that means I am grossly
under estimating the true value that is one
thing right. So that could be one condition
under which this could be true or it could
be another condition your grossly over estimating
the Ith value you are getting it, so either
I have to make a big mistake for my Q*, A*
or I have to make a big mistake the other
way for my I right you see that, right.
So I have to either come very down from a
true Q* value I mean a Q*, A* or I have to
be much above my normal value otherwise this
is not going to happen, right. So second condition
is, okay. Or when can it happen without me
grossly over estimating or under estimating
it? When the two values are close right if
the two values the A* value and the I value
are close to each other then I really do not
have to gross and under estimate these things.
So it is possible that I still could make
errors, right. So essentially the other condition
is right so I have my twice my take the confidents
interval right so I have a confidents interval
add here I will add from that side, right.
So I will add a confidents interval right
so I am taking twice the confidents interval
from my lower value right, from the lower
value I take twice the confidents interval.
In the topper value there is optimal actions
value lies within that right then I can make
a mistake without making a gross error also,
right I simply I am saying that these two
are close together, right. And close is a
relative term close is defined in terms of
the current uncertainty I have, right. Because
this is going to change every time I take
an action this is going to become smaller
and smaller, right.
So at the beginning of the learning this can
be fairly large so I can still make a mistake
right even if the means are slightly far apart,
right. So this is the 3 conditions one of
this at least will have to be satisfied for
these event to become true, second one says
when second one is easy man, so the first
one says okay I have my Q(A*) and I have my
confidents bound this is the first one okay
and the true Q*, A* is there, okay.
That means I have grossly under estimated
my Q*A* this is one condition, so the second
condition says this is Q(I) right and this
is Q*(I) so grossly overestimated by Q*(I)
this is essentially what the second condition
says so this is QI > Q*I + the confidents
one so this is the confidents bound so Q*I
+ this confidents bound will be only till
here, right. But QI is greater than that.
No, no is that eternal condition that can
hold right when both of these do not hold
also I could still be making a mistake right
I could still this could still be one if the
true means or not far apart with respect to
this error bar I have. See basically what
I am saying is, a true Q* could be somewhere
here right but I still can make a mistake
because it is too close. So probably draw
all this pictures and put it somewhere permanently.
Because every time I seem to be re-creating
this pictures, right. So I have first thing
I said okay the Q * is somewhere there right
I make a mistake right so and then I have
this guy right is possible for me to make
an error, right and then the other case was
okay this the true Q was somewhere here this
possible for me to make a mistake right this
third case say no none of this really need
to happen, right the true Q* could be well
within the boards right, but given the current
uncertainty I have in my Q(I) right, so the
true means are not so far apart right this
is uncertainty cannot over well made right
the true means are actually within the uncertainty.
Therefore, I could still make a mistake so
the first condition is not true the second
condition is not true but I still made the
mistake, okay.
So people have all of this expression everyone
has in their notebooks people who are writing
notes, people were not writing notes you have
this in your memory, because I am going to
erase it but I am going to write it again,
okay so I want to all of you to remember this.
.
Okay, so let us look at 1, so I want to look
at the probability that a* what did I do so
I want to bound that probability, right so
can I do that remember I told you Sn is Q,
I told you µ is Q* right, so we have they
already right, if you remember when I wrote
down the Hoeffding machine of bound, I told
you their comparison right, I told you that
Sn is Q µ is Q* so you have those there,
right. So essentially then a e becomes CM
right and by bound is e-2e2n right, and what
is Cn so it is 2lnn/s2.
.
Okay, then simplified and tell what is the
answer? So what is your n there, now what
is the n that you have yo plug in to the expression,
S this is where the thing became a little
messy because the paper is S as the, when
they introduce an addition notation, right
but I did not use that I try to use the t*
ta* notation itself, so it biomes ta* of S
that is that thing that you have to plug in,
okay so simplified and tell me what is the
answer.
.
So I plug in ta* of S here M here right, and
then I have to square it basically that is
my e that will get squared, right so my ta*
of S and my ta* of S get cancelled, right
I get ln m come on, after all that we have
done so far you could do this simplification
easily enough just substitute this into that
and then cancel things out and tell me what
is happening.
.
1/m4 right, so essentially this will be Sn
is equal to okay, so what about the second
term okay, what about the third term okay,
here is where we are going to use our mysterious
L right, what did L what did I introduce L
for I said that hey, I have done so many number
of trails already, okay I am only looking
at these events after that many number of
times I have taken our MI, right.
So I am going to make the following statement
if I taken sufficient number of trials initially
okay, if I have taken sufficient number of
pulls of form i initially this event will
never happen that is what I am claiming, right
this rather easy to see right, so what do
we have, we have q*a*-a*i-2Cm, okay right.
SO
essentially I am saying that my TiSi is at
least this much, right so that is what this
means right okay, say L is equal to this much
that means the number of times I have taken
are my is at least this much.
If you remember my Si ? starts from L right,
I consider Si only from L so if say L is this
so that means my TiSi is at least this much,
correct go and plug this into my Cn expression.
.
So if my S is this much at least this much
so what do I get, I get 2/8 ln m I mean ?a2
will go up so ln m, ln m will get cancel,
right so 2/8 will become 1/4 that is 1/2,
1/2 x?i right, so 1/2 and 1/2 2 will get cancelled
I will essentially get ?i, right so this expression
will become.
.
Okay, and what is this equal to, so for any
value of l greater than this, this quantity
will be greater than 0 that means this is
inequality will not fall, correct you people
see there you want me to do that again, yes
okay, so I am saying L is going to be at least
this much so then if you remember my TiSi
that the Si? is starting from L I am assuming
that at least L times I have taken this already,
right.
So I am assuming you have taken this L times
already so what I will do is L will plug the,
this value for the number of times I have
taken this already right this value, so I
will plug in 8 ln m this is Cm, S right so
this case look at the expression m, this so
this will be ln m right I am plugging in here
instead of S I will plug in 8 times ln m/?a2
right, ln m, ln m will get cancelled so 2/8
will become 1/4 and divide by ?a2 will go
up right, so I will basically get v?a2/4 which
is ?i/2, right.
So I will come and plug in ?i/2 here and 2
and 2 will get cancelled I will essentially
end up getting ?i here, so that is what I
have written here. So and by definition of
?i this expression is 0, right and for values
larger I mean if I take the ai more times
than this will essentially become
So this is you have done with UCB and they
have shown that UCB is regretted is bounded
and what is the nice thing we shown here is
that the regret grows as ln m right, and there
is a result from the 80s which tells us that
you cannot have a regret optimizing algorithm
that does better than ln m, right what you
can try to improve on is the 8, right this
is also impossible to get of that the ?i is
also impossible to get regret of you cannot
say that I will, I mean if the arms are close
in revote right, it becomes hard to eliminate
the bad arms, right. If they ate far away
in revote then you can quickly figure out
which are the bad arms but the arms are close
in revote and it becomes harder to figure
out so those things are always there.
So those are essential components with sop
basically people flied around with that date,
okay and yeah so that is essentially lot of
work that happens in regulate automate so
let to stop here because we have reached 5’o
greater than 0 and therefore that inequality
that I wanted will never hold, if I have taken
L at least if I have taken action i at least
L number times where L is given by that expression.
The third condition will never hold, okay
so the probability of the third condition
holding is 0 if L is greater than this, right.
So now what happens so the probability of
this whole thing happening is upper bounded
by just two times this probability right,
just add these events up so we are still not
done. Where are we, so are bounding the expected
value of the thing right, so we have expected
value of, so and I am going to say you to
write this out here okay.
So this is lesser than or equal 8ln m/?a2
because that is L plus the ? terms that we
had earlier right, and I am substituting a
specific value for L here okay, then what
will be the internal term here. Remember,
we have this random variable which could take
values of 1 or 0 so what is the expected value
of the random variable is just a probability
of it being 1, right so there are only two
of those things right.
So the probability of this event plus the
probability of this event, right that is basically
right so I am not writing down this because
this expression are going to take a long things
so probability of this event plus the probability
of that event so in which our case is just
m-4, m-4 that is essentially, right so it
is clear. So you see how that came up about,
right so here this was the random variable
right. Now once I took the expectation so
I can replace that random variable with the
probability of it being 1 that will be the
expectation of that random variable, okay
is it fine so replace that with the probability
of it being 1 is upper bounded m-4, m-4 and
that is basically here, okay great.
So this ? okay, I am going to declare it to
converge to 1+p2/3 okay, when you can little
involve thing but it is pure algebra okay
I mean you can work it out, okay or I mean
this is the standard relation you can look
it a person, right so that is basically what
we have. So this is kind of see that this
is going to because you going to be diminishing
some so it is going to converge to a limit,
right and so what is really interesting is
this part, right in some constant whatever
I said that it converges to it is not really
of interest you know not really of great interest
what is really of interest is this 8 ln m/?a,
right.
Because this is the one where you are going
to get mistake a lot because it has the ln
m term right, and it also has your ?i2, right
but this is the only expected value of Tin
but you have to multiplied by ?i to get the
total integrate and you have to some more
all i, right so that is essentially the thing
that we have finally that expression that
I erased here that is what you will end up
with that is why I said keep that in your
mind because that is the final expression
you are going to end up with, right.
This is for each arm this is for one suboptimal
arm, right this is a total number of times
you applied it right that is all we have derived
now, so the regretted due to that suboptimal
arm will be ?i times this number so that is
why the ?i2 goes to ?i in the denominator
in the original expression if you flip back
and you look at the original expression we
had a ?i here and we also had a 1+p2/3.?i.
but this is for one arm, so you have to do
this for all the suboptimal arms basically
that is why your ? is overall i which is not
optimal, okay great.
clock I
do not know if how many of
noticed it so if you have not I will take
that as I kept you successfully in gross,
but if people were just biting their time
to leave when I am apologies where keeping
here for so long, but I needed to finish this
right, I could not have stopped half way through
chart in the next class with 3? or something,
right.
So in the next class right, so we will look
at the last optimistic criterion was talking
about which was pack optimality, okay.